Sync and corrections by n17t01
www.addic7ed.com
中文字幕 @SaltyEggPain
宇    宙
时空探险之旅
第 3 集
当知识征服了恐惧
When Knowledge Conquered Fear
We were born into a mystery
我们的身世很神秘
one that has haunted us
这一直困扰着我们
since at least as long as we've been human.
自从人类诞生就是如此
We awakened on this tiny world
在这个星空覆盖下的小星球上
beneath a blanket of stars,
我们开始有了意识
like an abandoned baby left on a doorstep
就如同被遗弃在门口的婴儿
without a note to explain
没有留下只字片语
where we came from, who we are,
告诉我们是谁，我们从哪里来
how our universe came to be.
我们的世界会是怎样
And with no idea how to end our cosmic isolation.
我们在宇宙中是否还有其他同类
We've had to figure it all out for ourselves.
我们必须自己找出答案
Best thing we had going for us
我们最大的财富就是
was our intelligence,
我们的智慧
especially our gift for pattern recognition,
特别是识别模式的天赋
sharpened over eons of evolution.
经过远古以来进化过程的改造
The ones who were good at spotting prey and predator,
那些擅长区分猎物和猛兽的人
telling poisonous plants from the nourishing ones,
擅长识别有毒的食物的人
they had a better chance to live and reproduce.
他们活下去并繁衍的几率更大
They survived and passed on those genes
他们幸存下来 并把识别模式的基因传下去
for pattern recognition
with its obvious advantages.
优势显而易见
Cultures all over the planet
地球上的不同文化
looked up at the same stars
都是仰望同一个星空
and found different pictures there.
然后做出不同的解读
We used this gift for recognizing patterns in nature
我们用这种天赋在自然界中寻找模式
to read the calendar in the sky.
解读天空中的年历
The messages written in the stars
写在星空中的信息
told our forefathers and mothers
告诉我们的祖先
when to camp and when to move on.
何时安营  何时启程
When the migratory herds
兽群何时迁徙
and when the rains and the cold would come.
何时下雨  何时天寒
And when they would cease for a time.
何时他们可以停下来休息
When they observed the direct connection
当他们观察恒星间的运动与地球上
between the motions of the stars
and the seasonal cycles of life on Earth,
生命周期变化之间的直接联系
they concluded, naturally,
他们很自然地得出结论
that what happens up there
天上发生的变化
must be directed at us down here.
必然和地球上发生的事情息息相关
It makes sense, right?
也有道理 对吧
If the sky was a calendar
如果把天空看成日历
and somebody stuck a Post-it note on top of it,
有人在上面贴上一张便签纸
what else could it be but a message?
除了传达信息还会是什么
And so, when the heavenly order was suddenly violated
所以  当天空的秩序被突然打破时
by the apparition of a comet in the sky...
比如 当彗星划过天际时
they took it personally.
人们就会和自身联系起来
Can we really blame them?
也不能怪他们
Back then, they had no other logical explanation
那时 对于所发生的事情也没有其他
for what was happening.
符合逻辑的解释
This was long before
那是很久以前
anyone had yet to imagine Earth
没人会认为地球是个
as a spinning planet with a tilted axis,
倾斜自转的行星
revolving around the Sun.
绕着太阳公转
Every ancient human culture made the same mistake,
每种文化中的古人都犯过相同的错误
a comet must be a message,
彗星一定是来自众神
sent by the gods... or one particular god.
或某一个神的旨意
And almost invariably, our ancestors concluded
几乎是必然的  我们的祖先认为
the news was not good.
大事不妙
It didn't matter if you were an ancient Aztec,
不论你是古阿兹特克人
Anglo-Saxon, Babylonian, Hindu.
古英国人 古巴比伦人  古印度人
Comets were portents of doom.
彗星都是毁灭的前兆
The only difference among them
仅有的不同是
was the precise nature of the coming disaster.
灾难预报的精确程度
"Dis-aster," as in the Greek word for "bad star."
灾祸 源自希腊语中的 灾星
To the Masai of East Africa,
对东非的马塞人来说
a comet meant famine.
彗星意味着饥荒
To the Zulu in the south,
对南非的祖鲁人来说
it meant war.
意味着战争
To the Eghap people of the west,
对于西非的迦纳人来说
it meant disease.
意味着瘟疫
To the Djaga of Zaire,
对萨伊人（刚果）来说
specifically "smallpox."
特指 天花
To their neighbors, the Luba,
对于他们的邻居 陆巴人
a comet foretold the death of a leader.
彗星预示着领袖之死
The ancient Chinese were remarkably systematic.
古代中国人有着惊人的系统分类
Starting in roughly 1400 BC,
大约公元前1400年
they began recording and cataloguing
他们就开始了对彗星的
the apparitions of comets.
记录和分类
A three-tailed comet
三尾彗星
meant calamity for the state.
意味着国家的灾难
A four-tailed comet
四尾彗星
signified an epidemic was coming.
标志着瘟疫降临
The human talent for pattern recognition
人类识别模式的天赋
is a two-edged sword.
是把双刃剑
We're especially good at finding patterns,
我们尤其擅长寻找模式
even when they aren't really there--
哪怕无中生有
something known as "false pattern recognition."
或者 牵强附会
We hunger for significance,
我们渴望证明
for signs that our personal existence
人类的存在对这个宇宙
is of special meaning to the universe.
有着重大的意义
To that end, we're all too eager
说到底 我们的渴望
to deceive ourselves and others,
使我们宁愿相信
to discern a sacred image in a grilled cheese sandwich
烤面包上出现的圣像
or find a divine warning in a comet.
或者彗星带着上帝的旨意
Today, we know exactly where comets come from
今天 我们已经清楚知道了彗星的本质
and what they're made of.
Our Ship of the Imagination,
我们的想象之舟
fueled by equal parts of science and wonder,
由科学和好奇共同驱动
can take us anywhere in space and time.
可以带我们游历任何时空
It can travel faster than light
可以走的比光速还快
and render visible those things
可以呈现肉眼无法看见的事物
that cannot be seen.
It's carrying us to a mysterious realm
我们将进入一条神秘的溪流
that lies one light-year from the Sun.
距离太阳一光年的地方
What is this swarm of worlds?
众多的星体为何聚集
Was it organized by alien beings?
是由外星生物安排的吗
No.
不是
Just gravity.
万有引力而已
These are the snows of yesteryear,
历年的积雪
drifting mountains of ice and rock,
山峰般的寒冰和岩石
the preserved remnants of the birth of the solar system.
太阳系诞生时的剩余产物
It's called the Oort Cloud,
组成了 奥尔特云团
after Jan Oort, the Dutch astronomer
以荷兰天文学家奥尔特命名
who foretold its existence back in 1950.
他在1950年就预言了这个云团的存在
He was trying to solve a paradox.
他原本想解决一个悖论
There's so many ways for comets to die.
彗星有很多种消亡的方式
Because they cross the orbits of planets,
因为它们会穿过行星的轨道
comets frequently collide with them.
经常发生碰撞
Comets are largely made of ice,
彗星很大程度上由冰组成
so every time they come near the Sun,
所以 每次接近太阳时
they lose a part of themselves through evaporation.
它们会蒸发掉一部分
And after several thousand trips,
这个过程重复几千次
their ice is all gone,
所有的冰 蒸发了
and what remains of the comet is now an asteroid.
残余的彗星就是现在的小行星
Comets can be gravitationally ejected from the solar system
彗星被太阳系的引力场排斥
and exiled into space.
流放至太空
And yet, somehow,
无论如何
the comets keep coming.
彗星总会回来
Oort and other astronomers wondered,
奥尔特和其他天文学家自忖
"Where do all the comets come from?"
这些彗星都是哪里来的
Oort calculated the rate at which new comets appear
奥尔特通过计算新彗星出现的比率
and concluded that there must be
得出结论
a vast, spherical swarm of them,
由数量极多的彗星组成一个
a few light-years across,
直径达到几光年的
surrounding the Sun.
园球状包围太阳
Oort's logic still holds up,
奥尔特的理论时至今日依然成立
even after all the discoveries we've made about comets
哪怕是几十年后  我们对彗星和太阳系
and the solar system in the many decades since.
有了更多的认识的今天
And yet, the Oort Cloud is a sight
不过  奥尔特云团是个
that no one has ever seen.
无人能看到的景象
Nor could we.
我们也不行
It's dark out here.
那里漆黑一片
And each comet is about as far from its closest neighbor
最近的两个彗星间的距离就如同
as the Earth is from Saturn.
地球到土星的距离
But science gives us special powers of our own.
但是 科学给我们特殊的能力
It gave Jan Oort
科学给了奥尔特
the gift of prophecy.
预见的天赋
Oort was also the first to correctly estimate
奥尔特也是第一个正确估计出
the distance between the Sun and the center of our galaxy.
太阳到银河系中心的距离
That's a big deal--
这是很了不起的成就
finding out where we are in the Milky Way.
找到了我们在银河系的位置
Our star is about
我们的恒星
30,000 light-years from the center.
距离中心3万光年
Oort was also
奥尔特也是首个
the first guy to use a radio telescope
使用射电望远镜
to map the galaxy's spiral structure.
绘制出了银河系的螺旋结构
And he discovered that the center of our galaxy
并且 他发现银河系的中心
was a place of titanic explosions,
发生着一连串极大的爆炸
the first indication that there might have been
这是第一个迹象 显示出那里可能
a supermassive black hole lurking there.
暗藏着一个巨大的黑洞
Does the fact that most of us know
事实上 我们中的很多人
the names of mass murderers,
知道著名杀人魔的名字
but never heard of Jan Oort,
却从没听说过奥尔特
say anything about us?
人性就是如此
The Oort Cloud is so enormous
奥尔特云团是如此巨大
that it takes one of its comets about a million years
彗星要用100万年
to complete a single trip around the Sun.
才能绕太阳一圈
Out here, at the far edge of the solar system,
在这里 太阳系的边缘
even a little tug from the gravity of a passing star
即使擦肩而过的星星产生的轻微引力
can liberate some of these comets
也会使这些彗星
from their gravitational bondage to the Sun.
摆脱太阳引力的束缚
Some comets are flung out of the solar system
一些彗星被抛出太阳系
to wander interstellar space.
从此在星际空间游荡
But for others, there's a different fate.
其他的一些彗星 却有着不同的命运
This one is plunging towards the Sun,
这颗彗星被抛向太阳
gaining speed in an unbroken free fall
在无阻力的自由落体中不断加速
that lasts hundreds of thousands of years.
一直持续几十万年
When Neptune's gravity gives it another tug,
当海王星的引力再次吸引它时
there's a small change in course.
它的轨迹发生了小小的变化
Mighty Jupiter, the most massive
强大的木星
object in our solar system--
太阳系中质量最大的物体
other than the Sun-- attracts the comet
除太阳以外
with its powerful gravitational pull, bending its path.
用它强大的引力再次改变彗星的轨迹
When our comet reaches the inner solar system...
当这颗彗星到达太阳系的核心
heat from the Sun bakes it.
太阳的热量烘烤着它
A beautiful transformation begins.
一场美丽的转变开始了
The barren, sooty iceberg
被烟熏黑的贫瘠冰山
now sports a glowing halo...
变幻出灼热的光晕
and a tail.
还有彗尾
These layers tell the story of how the comet was made,
这些层次描述着大约40亿年前
some four billion years ago.
彗星产生的过程
During the 40,000 generations of humanity,
在4万代人的历史中
there must have been roughly 100,000 apparitions
至少有大约10万次
of a bright comet.
耀眼的彗星划过天际
For all that time,
那个时候
the best we could do was look up in helpless wonder,
我们只能仰望  不禁的惊叹
prisoners of Earth with nowhere to turn
无助的人们不知所措
for an explanation beyond our guilt and our fears.
除了恐惧和悔恨 没有更好的办法
But then a friendship began between two men that led
后来 两个人的友情为人类的思想
to a permanent revolution in human thought.
带来了翻天覆地的革命
Isaac Newton and Edmond Halley could not know it,
艾萨克·牛顿和愛德蒙·哈雷 也是始料未及
but their collaboration would ultimately set us free
他们的研究成果将我们从
这颗小星球的局限中彻底解放
from our long confinement on this tiny world.
他们的研究成果将我们从
这颗小星球的局限中彻底解放
The Comet of 1664
1664年的这颗彗星
sent shivers of dread throughout Europe,
令整个欧洲恐惧颤栗
and the terror seemed justified when the Plague
随后发生的大瘟疫和伦敦大火灾
and the Great Fire of London followed soon after.
恰巧印证了人们的恐惧
There, with long bloody hair,
那血色的长发
a blazing star threatens the world
耀眼的星辰威胁整个世界
with famine, plague and war.
带来饥荒  瘟疫 战争
To princes, it spells death...
王子们的死亡
to kingdoms, many crosses...
王国多了无数的墓碑
to all estates, inevitable losses...
不可避免的财产损失
to herdsmen, rot,
腐烂的牧群
to plowmen, hapless seasons,
颗粒无收的庄稼汉
to sailors, it brings storms,
海上的风暴
to cities, civil treasons.
暴动的市民
But for one child,
但有一个孩子
the comet was not the least bit frightening.
并不觉得彗星有那么恐怖
For him, it was a thing of wonder.
对他来说 只是惊奇
Like all of us, Edmond Halley was born curious.
和我们一样  愛德蒙·哈雷生性好奇
Hell's bells!
哇塞
He was lucky to have a father who
encouraged and nurtured his curiosity,
他很幸运  他的父亲支持并鼓励他的求知欲
He was lucky to have a father who
encouraged and nurtured his curiosity,
他很幸运  他的父亲支持并鼓励他的求知欲
buying him the best scientific instruments
给他买了最好的科学仪器
and even funding his expedition
资助他的探险考察
to make the first accurate star
map of the Southern Hemisphere.
为了画出第一张精确的南半球星空图
Halley dropped out of Oxford when he was 20,
哈雷20岁时从牛津辍学
and sailed to St. Helena,
去了圣赫勒拿岛
an island below the equator,
off the west coast of Africa.
一个位于赤道以南  非洲的西海岸的小岛
Hell's bells.
哇塞
The problem was, nobody told Halley
问题是 没人告诉哈雷
that the weather on St. Helena
岛上的天气状况是如此糟糕
was generally lousy; it took
him 12 frustrating months
他用了12个月
to observe enough southern
stars to make a complete map.
才观测到足够的南半球星星来绘制完整的星图
The gods and heroes of ancient Greece were now joined
古希腊的众神和英雄人物
by the mythic figures of a new world and age,
由虚构的图形将它们汇聚在一起
a toucan, a compass,
a bird of paradise.
巨喙鸟  指南针  天堂鸟
When Halley came home
with the other half of the sky,
当哈雷带着《南天星表》回到家时
his map created a sensation.
他的星空图造成了轰动
Now merchants and explorers could navigate
by the stars visible anywhere on Earth.
商人和探险家可以根据随处可见的星星导航
Now merchants and explorers could navigate
by the stars visible anywhere on Earth.
商人和探险家可以根据随处可见的星星导航
At the time, the World Society of London
当时 伦敦的皇家学会
was the world's clearinghouse of scientific discovery.
是世界上科学发现的集散地
Its motto, "Nullius in verba,"
它的格言是 不人云亦云
sums up the heart of the scientific method.
总结出了科学方法的中心思想
It's Latin for "see for yourself."
它是拉丁语中的 亲自求证
In other words, "question authority."
换言之 质疑权威
Halley's star maps caught the attention
哈雷的星图引起了学会实验室负责人的注意
of the Society's Curator of Experiments.
I'd show him to you if I could,
我也想让你看看他的样子
but no portrait of Robert Hooke exists from his time,
但罗伯特·胡克并没有留下任何的肖像画
only the verbal descriptions of his contemporaries.
只有他的事迹口耳相传
They called him "lean, bent, ugly."
他们说他 瘦弱 驼背 丑陋
He was possibly the most
inventive person who ever lived.
他可能是最有创造性的天才
And despite his appearance,
不论他的外表如何
he was the most sought-after
party guest in all of London.
他在当时的伦敦炙手可热
Why?
为何
Hooke's insatiable curiosity
胡克永不满足的求知欲
encompassed absolutely everything.
覆盖了所有的领域
Hooke discovered a little cosmos,
胡克发现了一个小宇宙
and we still call it by the name he gave it, the cell.
我们至今沿用他给它的命名  细胞(cell)
Hooke discovered the cell by looking
胡克通过观察一片软木片发现了细胞
at a piece of cork with one of his own inventions,
正是用了他自己的一项发明
the compound microscope.
复合显微镜
He anticipated aspects of
Darwin's theory of evolution
他提出的观点比达尔文的进化论
by almost 200 years.
早了几乎200年
Hooke also improved the telescope.
胡克又改良了望远镜
The drawings he made of the
astronomical bodies he observed
他根据观察天体所做的素描
attest to his uncanny precision.
见证了他异乎寻常的准确性
After the Great Fire destroyed
central London in 1666,
1666年的伦敦大火灾摧毁了伦敦中部
Hooke partnered with the architect Christopher Wren
胡克与建筑师 克里斯多佛·雷恩合作
to redesign and rebuild the city.
重新设计 建设 伦敦
Hooke was the foremost experimentalist of his age.
胡克是当时首屈一指的实验主义者
Using coiled springs,
使用弹簧
he derived the "law of elasticity,"
他提出了 弹性定律
known today as Hooke's Law.
我们称之为  胡克定律
He perfected the air pump,
他改良了气泵
the height of technology in its time,
达到了当时的技术顶峰
and used it to experiment on respiration and sound.
并将之用于声音和呼吸实验
And he experimented with cannabis.
他用大麻做实验
He reported to a meeting
of the Royal Society
他在一次皇家学会的会议上报告
that a sea captain friend of his
据他的一位船长朋友说
"had so often experimented with it,
“经常食用这个东西
that there is no cause of fear,
不会令人产生恐惧
though possibly there may be of laughter."
只会带来喜悦”
But coffee was the drug of choice for England
咖啡在17世纪的英格兰
in the 17th century.
是最受欢迎的
Coffeehouses sprang up all over London.
咖啡馆遍布伦敦
This is where people came to get news,
人们在那里获取新闻
to launch new ventures, and to debate ideas.
发表新的观点 讨论时事
The coffeehouse was an oasis of equality
咖啡馆是这个注重阶级的社会中
in a class-obsessed society.
平等的绿洲
Here, a poor man needn't give up his seat
在这里  穷人不需要给富人让座
to a rich man, nor submit to his opinion.
也不用屈从他的观点
It was a kind of laboratory of democracy.
就像是民主制度的实验室
In this highly caffeinated atmosphere,
在这种高度兴奋刺激的气氛中
Halley and Hooke met Christopher
Wren to discuss a deep mystery.
哈雷和胡克 与克里斯多佛·雷恩讨论着一个谜团
Why do the planets move as they do?
为何行星如此运动
The astronomer Johannes Kepler had demonstrated,
天文学家约翰内斯·开普勒在此前的
some 80 years before,
80多年 就证明了
that the orbits of the planets around the Sun
行星绕太阳公转的轨道
were not perfect circles, but actually ellipses,
并不是正圆  而是椭圆形
and that the closer a planet was to the Sun,
行星越靠近太阳
the faster it moved.
运动的越快
Why?
为什么
Could some invisible force
from the Sun be responsible
会是太阳发出某些看不见的力量
for this change in motion?
导致这种变化吗
If so, how did it work?
如果是  又是如何导致的呢
Could there be a simple mathematical law to describe it?
可以用一个简单的数学定律描述吗
Maybe something like Hooke's Law of Elasticity?
就像胡克的弹性定律那样
Perhaps.
有可能
But try as he might,
但是 尝试之后
Christopher Wren couldn't figure it out.
克里斯多佛·雷恩没有答案
Damned if I haven't tried.
总好过没有尝试过
It's beyond me.
我的能力有限
I'll wager a book worth 40 shillings
我押上这本价值40先令的书
to the man who can solve it!
谁能解决 谁就拿去
That book is mine, Mr. Wren.
我拿定了  雷恩先生
I've already done the calculation.
我已经完成了计算
Halley was delighted.
哈雷非常开心
Show us, Mr. Hooke.
快让我们见识见识  胡克先生
But months passed, and Hooke failed to deliver.
但几个月过去  胡克也没能做到
He couldn't do the math.
他算不过来
None of them could.
没人能够
Finally, Halley had enough of Hooke's excuses.
最后 哈雷厌烦了胡克的借口
Halley knew there must be someone, somewhere,
哈雷知道 肯定在某个地方 有某个人
up to the challenge.
可以做到
What about that mathematician at Cambridge?
剑桥大学的数学家怎么样
Clever fellow.
聪明的家伙
He had solved central questions about the nature of light
他多年前就解决了光线本质的核心问题
years before, when he was still only 22.
他当时只有22岁
And he invented the reflecting telescope.
他发明了反射望远镜
Odd bird.
怪人
Dropped out of sight a while back;
销声匿迹过一段时间
some squabble over Hooke
and his discovery about light.
因为他的光学发现与胡克发生争吵
Went completely to pieces over it
走了极端  无法自拔
and has been hiding out
in Cambridge ever since.
从此在剑桥大学隐居
Halley wondered if this strange, and by all accounts,
哈雷很期待 这个怪人
exceedingly difficult man, might succeed
据说 很难相处的人
where Hooke and others had failed.
是否能成功
What he couldn't know,
他当时并不知道
what no one could possibly
imagine at the time,
没有任何人会想到
were the countless ways
整个世界
the world would be forever
changed by this meeting
各个方面都因为这次见面而从此改变
on an August day in 1684.
就在1684年8月的某一天
Isaac Newton was born in England
艾萨克·牛顿出生于英格兰
on Christmas Day in 1642.
1642年的圣诞节 （欧洲旧历）
Before he even opened his eyes,
his father was already dead.
父亲在他出生前就过世了
His mother left him when he was only three
3岁时 母亲也抛弃了他
and did not return until he was 11.
直到11岁才再次见面
When she did, it was
with a new family and husband,
她已经有了新的家庭
a stepfather who Isaac Newton despised.
牛顿鄙视他的继父
Newton's refuge from his miserable family life
悲惨家庭环境中的唯一避风港
was his passion to understand how things worked,
就是牛顿对于科学研究的热情
especially nature itself.
特别是自然科学
In 1661, the talented young
Isaac entered Trinity College at Cambridge University
1661年  天资聪颖的艾萨克进了剑桥大学三一学院
where he was a consistently lousy student,
他在学校很不合群
one without friends or a loving family
没有家人和朋友
to provide any warmth or encouragement.
给他丝毫的温暖和鼓励
Newton mostly kept to himself,
sequestered in his room,
牛顿不与人交流  把自己关在房间里
studying ancient Greek philosophers,
学习古希腊的哲学
geometry and languages,
几何和语言
and pondering deep questions
琢磨着更深层次的问题
on the nature of matter, space, time, and motion.
关于自然  空间  时间  运动
This budding scientist was also a passionate mystic.
这位才华初露的科学家也是一名狂热的神秘主义者
Newton believed that a secret knowledge
牛顿相信这种只为小部分
called alchemy, known only to a small group
古代哲学家所知的炼金术
of ancient philosophers,
was waiting to be rediscovered.
正等着他去重新发现
He hoped to learn how to change ordinary metals
他希望可以学会把普通金属
into silver and gold,
变成金银的方法
and maybe even cook up the elixir of life,
或许可以做出生命合剂
the key to to immortality.
以此长生不老
He was also obsessed
他一心想从圣经的字里行间
with finding hidden messages
in the words of the Bible.
找到隐藏的信息
He combed through translations
in several different languages,
他梳理了不用语言的译本
hoping to decipher coded
instructions from God.
试图破译加密了的上帝的指示
He made elaborate calculations
in an effort
他做了详尽的计算
to discover the date of the Second Coming.
只为发现基督再次降临的日期
His lifelong research in alchemy
穷其一生研究炼金术
and biblical chronology never led anywhere.
研究圣经  并没有任何突破
When Halley found Newton that fateful day,
当哈雷找到牛顿的那天
he was living as a virtual recluse.
牛顿一直过着隐居的生活
Newton had gone into hiding 13 years earlier,
牛顿自从罗伯特·胡克公开指责他
after Robert Hooke had publicly
accused Newton of stealing
剽窃胡克关于光学和颜色的突破性成果
his groundbreaking work on light and color.
已经隐居了13年
In fact, it was Isaac Newton
事实上 牛顿才是那个
who solved the mystery of the spectrum of light,
解开光谱谜团的人
not Robert Hooke.
并不是罗伯特·胡克
This wound was painful and deep,
这对他的打击很大
and Newton resolved to never
expose himself to that kind
牛顿下定决心从此再不让自己陷入
of public humiliation ever again.
那种被人羞辱的境地
Sir, I don't suppose you recall
先生 你可能不记得了
our meeting a few years ago?
我们几年前见过
Yes, Mr. Halley.
我记得 哈雷先生
I'm sorry to bother you.
抱歉来打搅你
Never mind the formalities,
get to your point.
不用客套 有话直说
I've been talking with our
friends, Mr. Wren and Mr. Hooke.
我一直与我们的朋友  胡克和雷恩在讨论
That scoundrel Hooke's
no friend of mine.
胡克那个人渣不是我的朋友
Yes, I understand, sir.
我明白
But the thing is we've been debating
重点是 我们一直在讨论
the puzzling question of planetary motion.
行星运动的难题
We all agree that some force of attraction
我们都认同 某种吸引的力量
from the Sun governs the motions of the planets.
来自太阳  控制着行星的运动
We suspect there must be a mathematical law
我们感觉一定能有一条数学定律
to describe how this force
来形容这种
changes with distance.
根据距离而改变的力量
And knowing of your skill...
以您的能力
Yes, yes, the attraction of gravity
没错 重力所产生的吸引力
weakens with the square of the distance.
与距离的平方成反比
That's why the planets move in ellipses.
这就是椭圆轨道的原因
But, sir, how can you know this?
但您是怎么知道的
Why, I have calculated it some five years ago.
怎么了 我5年多前就算出来了
I beg you, show it to me.
求你了 让我见识一下
The calculation is here...
计算的结果在这里
somewhere.
就在周围
Well, no matter.
没关系
I shall redo it and be sure
我重新做一份
to send it on to you.
然后寄给你
This is stupendous!
太不可思议了
Why have we not had word of it before?
相见恨晚啊
Newton remembered all too well
牛顿还记得上次
what Hooke had done to him
他提出新的理论时
the last time he put forth an idea.
胡克的所作所为
Just when Halley may have begun to wonder
就在哈雷开始怀疑
if Newton was bluffing as Hooke had done earlier,
牛顿是否也像胡克那样吹牛时
a messenger arrived
with an envelope from Newton.
信使带来牛顿的一封信
Here are the opening pages
of modern science
这是现代科学理论的开篇
with its all-embracing vision of nature...
包含了对于大自然的洞察
universal laws of motion, gravity...
运动定律  万有引力
not just for the Earth,
不单适用于地球
but for the cosmos.
也适用于整个宇宙
Halley raced back to Cambridge.
哈雷迫不及待地回到剑桥
Mr. Newton, I beseech you
to work all of this
牛顿大人  我求你赶紧
into a book as soon as possible.
把这些都写进你的书里吧
I can assure you the Royal
Society will publish it.
我向你保证 一定让皇家学会出版
But there was one little problem.
但还有一个小问题
We are in agreement
我们同意
that Mr. Newton has produced a masterpiece.
牛顿先生的成果是伟大的
However, I'm afraid the Royal Society has...
但是  皇家学会恐怕
well, regrettably sales for the History of Fish...
鱼类历史的惨淡销售
have not lived up to our financial expectations.
我们的财政状况并不乐观
It's an impressive book.
这是一本很棒的书
Extremely comprehensive.
包罗万象
Really.
真的
It's filled with lavish illustrations of...
使用了大量的插图来描述
well, fish.
鱼类
The disappointing sales led to a bigger problem.
惨淡的销售带来更大的问题
The Royal Society pretty much blew
皇家学会在出版鱼类历史上
its total annual budget on the History of Fish.
几乎用尽整年的预算
In fact, they were so strapped for cash,
他们现金短缺
they had to pay poor Halley's salary
他们不得不用那卖不掉的书
with copies of their worst-selling book.
来抵本应支付给哈雷的工资
With no money to print
Newton's Principia,
没有钱来印刷牛顿的《原理》
the scientific revolution
hung in the balance.
科学革命 命悬一线
Without Halley's heroic efforts,
要不是哈雷的努力
the reclusive Newton's masterwork
牛顿的这部巨著
might never have seen the light of day.
可能永无出头之日
But Halley was a man on a mission,
哈雷的坚持不懈
absolutely determined to bring
Newton's genius to the world.
将牛顿的天才展现给了全世界
That pre-scientific world,
那个科学革命以前
the world ruled by fear,
靠恐惧来统治的世界
was poised at the edge of a revolution.
已经被推向了革命的边缘
Everything depended
on whether or not Edmond Halley
一切就看爱德蒙·哈雷能否
could get Newton's book out to the wider world.
将牛顿的新书推向世界
Halley resolved not only to edit Newton's book,
哈雷编辑并且出版了牛顿的书
but to publish it at his own expense.
自掏腰包
Newton completed the first two volumes,
在牛顿完成的头两卷里
laying the mathematical framework
用数学公式
for the physics of motion.
来描述物理运动
The third volume would settle once and for all
第三卷彻底决定了谁才是咖啡馆的
who won the coffeehouse wager.
赌局赢家
Newton applied his principles to explain
牛顿运用他的原理可以解释
all the known motions of the Earth,
地球上所有的运动
the Moon and the planets.
月亮和其他行星
Unfortunately, there was this problem.
不幸的是 还有一个问题
Now Halley also took on the role
哈雷又变成了
of Newton's psychotherapist.
牛顿的心理医生
Isaac, I'm afraid that Mr. Hooke requires
艾萨克  内个  胡克先生要求
an acknowledgment in
the preface of your third volume.
在你的第三卷序言里向他致谢
But I have done so.
我已经做过了啊
Thanking him, Mr. Wren and yourself
谢谢他，雷恩先生还有你
for prodding me to think again
on astronomical matters.
激励我重新思考有关天文学的事情
Mr. Hooke has been going about London saying
胡克在伦敦到处说
that you got the Law of Gravity from him.
你的万有引力定律是借鉴了他
Why, that litigious little...
我要告他这个小...
Never!
做梦
I would sooner burn the third volume
我宁可烧了我的第三卷
than deface it with such a lie.
也不会让这种谎言玷污它
To hell with Hooke.
让胡克去死吧
He will be long forgotten
他会被人们遗忘
when your ideas are still being celebrated.
而你的理论会被人们永远歌颂
More copies of that dreadful book?
又是这些恶心的书
Wherever shall we put them all?
家里都快放不下了
We talked about this, Mary, dear.
我和你说过的 玛丽 亲爱的
This is my salary from the Society.
这是科学院给我的薪水
They have nothing else with which to pay me.
他们也拿不出其他东西了
If only Mr. Hooke and Mr. Newton were more like you.
如果胡克和牛顿也能像你这样就好了
Halley and Wren decided to confront Hooke
哈雷和雷恩决定和胡克对质
about his false claims.
关于他不实的言论
That law is mine, I tell you!
那是我的定律 我告诉你
I proved it first.
我先证明的
Then fetch your proof here at once.
那就把你的证据拿出来
Let us see it.
让我们看看
Surely we have waited on it long enough.
反正我们都等了这么久了
You'll simply have to take my word for it.
你只要相信我的话就可以了
Empty claims may persuade elsewhere,
空口无凭或许在其他地方行得通
but not here.
但这里不行
Put up or shut up, Mr. Hooke.
拿不出来就闭嘴  胡克先生
Blasted Newton. I'll make him pay.
牛顿这个混蛋  我要他付出代价
If it wasn't for Edmond Halley,
如果没有爱德蒙·哈雷
Newton's great book would've
never been conceived,
牛顿绝没有机会构思
nor written, nor printed.
书写 出版他的书
Okay. So what?
好吧  那又怎样
What difference does that make to us?
对我们来说有什么不一样
What's the big deal?
有什么大不了的
When Isaac Newton was born in this house
当牛顿在这栋房子里诞生时
in 1642, the world was very different.
1642年  那时的世界和现在完全不一样
Everyone looked at the perfection
每个人看到天空中的众多星星
of the clockwork motions of the planets in the sky
像钟表一样的准确运行
and could only understand it as the work
只能想到的是出自
of a master clock maker.
一个伟大的“钟表匠”
How else to explain it?
还能怎么解释
There was only one way
such a thing could come about
他们只能想出一种解释
in their imagination;
以他们的想象力
only one answer for them--
只有一种答案
God.
上帝
For reasons beyond our understanding,
出于我们还不了解的原因
God just created the solar system that way.
上帝就是这么创造的太阳系
But this explanation is the closing of a door.
这个解释却是一种关门主义
It doesn't lead to other questions.
它没有引导我们提出其他问题
Along came Newton,
牛顿来了
a God-loving man
who's also a genius.
上帝宠爱的人  大天才
He could write the laws of nature
他能用完美的数学语句
in perfect mathematical sentences--
写出大自然的定律
formulas that applied universally
对宇宙有效的方程式
to apples, moons, planets
对苹果 月亮 行星都有效
and so much more.
还有很多
With one foot still in the Middle Ages,
虽然仍身处中世纪
Isaac Newton imagined the whole solar system.
牛顿已经想象出了整个太阳系
Newton's laws of gravity and motion
牛顿的万有引力和运动定律
revealed how the Sun held distant worlds captive.
揭示了太阳如何维系这些遥远的星球
His laws swept away the need
他的定律使人们不再需要
for a master clock maker
用“钟表匠”来解释
to explain the precision
and beauty of the solar system.
为什么太阳系能如此精准的运行
Gravity is the clock maker.
万有引力就是钟表匠
Matter obeyed commandments
we could discover,
事物遵循我们发现的戒律运动
laws the Bible hadn't mentioned.
遵循圣经没有提到过的定律运动
Newton's answer to why the
solar system is the way it is
牛顿的理论解释了为什么太阳子会是这样的
opened the way to an infinite number of questions.
也为其他无数的问题打开了大门
Principia also happened to include
《原理》的内容里包括
the invention of calculus,
微积分的发明
and the first sound theoretical basis
还有第一个坚实的理论基础
for an end to our imprisonment on Earth--
为我们打破了地球的枷锁
space travel.
太空旅行
Newton envisioned the firing of a cannonball...
牛顿设想 发射出去的炮弹
with increasingly greater explosive thrust.
随着爆炸推力的增加
He reasoned that with enough velocity,
只要速度足够快
the bounds of gravity could be broken,
就可以突破引力的界限
and the cannonball could escape
炮弹就可以离开地球
to orbit the Earth.
绕地球旋转
This changed everything.
这 改变了 整个世界
Newton's Principia Mathematica
set us free in another way.
牛顿的数学原理 将我们彻底解放
By finding the natural laws
通过找到控制彗星运行的自然定律
governing the comings and goings of comets,
he decoupled the motions
of the heavens
他使我们摆脱了天体运行所带来的恐惧
from their ancient connections to our fears.
不再像我们的祖先那样
If Halley hadn't been standing
next to Newton for all those years,
如果哈雷没有竭尽全力的支持牛顿
perhaps the world would remember him
for his own accomplishments and discoveries.
人们可能会记住他自己的发现和成就
But the only thing that comes
to mind for most people
而不是 仅仅记住一个彗星的名字
is the comet, the irony is that discovering a comet
讽刺的是  发现彗星这件事
is actually one of the few things that Halley never did.
其实哈雷从没有做过
有冰山
左满舵
After the publication of the Principia
《原理》出版后
Halley was commanded by
his king to lead three ocean voyages,
哈雷奉命带领3艘大船  出海科学考察
scientific expeditions to solve
navigational problems for the British navy.
为英国海军解决导航的问题
Halley used this opportunity to make
the first map of the Earth's magnetic field
哈雷利用这次机会  绘制了第一张地球磁场图
And he was also a businessman.
他同时也是个商人
Halley perfected the diving bell...
哈雷改良了潜水钟
...and used his invention to start
并用他的发明
a flourishing commercial salvage operation.
开创了繁荣的商业打捞业务
Mmm, ah, Dr. Halley's gone and done it this time.
嗯 哈雷博士这次是真的做到了
I reckon he's been down there at least three hours.
我看他在下面最少3个小时了
Not one to risk the lives of others,
没人拿其他人的生命冒险
Halley personally tested his own invention.
哈雷亲自测试他的发明
I make it exactly four hours since our descent.
下来以后已经坚持了4个小时
Not at all bad for ten fathoms.
对10英寻（18米）的深度来说不错了
He invented the weather map.
他发明了气象图
And the symbols he devised
for indicating prevailing winds
他设计的标示盛行风的符号
are still in use today.
一直沿用至今
Halley laid the groundwork
哈雷为人口统计学
for the science of population statistics.
打下了坚实的基础
How?
怎么做的
He compared the birth, marriage, death,
他对比伦敦和巴黎的出生 结婚 死亡人数
and population densities
of London and Paris.
以及人口密度
He actually had to pace off
他真的用双脚
the entire perimeter of Paris, on foot,
测量出巴黎的周长
to learn its true dimensions.
只为计算正确的面积
He came to the conclusion
他总结出
that since roughly half of all adults fail
既然大约一半的成年人
to reproduce children,
无法生孩子
who themselves survive to reproduce,
要繁衍他们的基因
every married couple must have four children
每对夫妻必须要有4个孩子
in order to maintain the population.
才能保持人口数量
And it was Edmond Halley who gave us
爱德蒙 哈雷告诉我们
the actual scale of the solar system.
太阳系的实际比例
He figured out a clever way
to find the distance
他找到一个聪明的办法算出
from Earth to the Sun.
地球到太阳的距离
It involved precisely measuring the time it took
通过精确地测量
for the planet Venus to cross the Sun's disc.
金星穿过日面所用的时间（金星凌日）
27 years after Halley's death,
哈雷过世后的27年
Captain James Cook made
his first voyage to Tahiti
詹姆士库克船长第一次到达塔希提岛
for the express purpose
of testing Halley's method
为了验证哈雷的方法
during a transit of Venus
across the Sun.
在观察金星凌日的过程中
Using a special filter
to protect his vision
他用一种特殊的滤镜保护眼睛
from being destroyed
by looking directly at the Sun,
防止直视太阳带来的损伤
Cook and his men made it
possible for us to know
库克团队的努力使我们知道
that the Sun is 93 million miles from Earth.
太阳距离地球9300万英里（1.5亿公里）
And Halley was the first to realize
哈雷也是第一个认识到
that the so-called "fixed" stars were not fixed at all.
所谓的恒星 并非静止不动
How'd he do it?
他是怎么知道的
He pored over the observations made
他将古希腊天文学家
by the ancient Greek astronomers of the brightest stars.
对最明亮的星星的观测结果
And he compared their
observations with the ones
与他在1800年后观测的同一颗星星的
he himself made of the same stars 1,800 years later.
观测结果作比较
Why hadn't anyone noticed
this before?
为什么之前没人注意到
Halley figured out that it would only become apparent
哈雷意识到要想观察出来
if you waited long enough between observations.
两次的观测时间要间隔很长才行
It's hard to perceive the motions of things
要观察到相距遥远的物体间的移动
that are far away.
是很困难的
And the stars are so very far away,
而且恒星间的距离是如此的遥远
that you would need to track them for many centuries
要花几百年的时间去观察
before you could detect that they moved at all.
才能察觉它们的移动
Halley discovered the first clue to a magnificent reality,
哈雷发现了一个宏伟的现实
all the stars are in motion, streaming past each other,
所有的恒星都在运动 相互赶超
rising and falling like merry-go-round horses
和旋转木马一样上升和降落
in their Newtonian dance around the center of our galaxy.
在银河系中此起彼伏
And, oh, yes, there was that thing about the comet.
对了 还有彗星的事情
What were those strange and
beautiful celestial visitors
这些美丽的陌生天外访客到底是谁
that appeared without warning from time to time?
时不时的突然造访
Halley set out to solve this
mystery as a detective would,
哈雷用侦探常用的方法来解决这个谜团
by gathering all credible eyewitness testimony.
搜集所有可靠目击证人的证词
The earliest precise observations of a comet
哈雷能找到的最早准确观察到
that Halley could find were made in Constantinople
彗星的证人是位于君士坦丁堡的
by Nikephoros Gregoras, a Byzantine astronomer and monk
尼斯波罗斯·贵格列 拜占庭帝国的天文学家兼僧人
in June 1337.
1337年6月
Halley hunted down every astronomical observation
哈雷收集了1472-1698年间所有的
of a comet recorded in Europe between 1472 and 1698.
在欧洲的彗星观测记录
And remember, there was no such thing
请记住 那时还没有
as a search engine or a computer.
搜索引擎 或者电脑
All Halley had
were his books and his mind.
哈雷只能依靠他的书和大脑
Now here comes the hard part,
困难的地方到了
Halley had to take the
observations made for each comet
哈雷必须要按照每个彗星的观察结果
and find the shape of its
actual path through space.
在太空中找出实际的运动轨迹
No one else but Newton had yet attempted
除了牛顿 没人尝试过
to apply his new set of laws to an astronomical question.
将他的定律应用于天文学的问题
In an arduous tour de force of mathematical brilliance,
这是一次艰巨的数学运算的壮举
Halley discovered that comets were bound to the Sun
哈雷发现彗星被太阳束缚在
in long elliptical orbits.
长椭圆的轨道上
And he was the first to know
that the comets seen in 1531,
他是第一个知道1531年发现的那个彗星
1607, and 1682...
和1607年 还有1682年发现的
were one and the same--
是同一颗彗星
a single comet that returned every 76 years.
每隔76年回归一次
In a stunning example
of true pattern recognition,
这是模式识别的绝佳例子
he predicted
it would be seen again
他预测在超过50年后的未来
more than 50 years in the future.
这颗彗星还会回归
For millennia, comets had been props for mystics,
上千年来 彗星都很神秘
who considered them to be
merely omens of human events.
被巫师们视为人类事件的预兆
Halley shattered their monopoly,
哈雷打破了他们的垄断
beating them at their own game,
以他们熟悉的领域里
a game that no scientist
had ever played before...
以前没有科学家进入过的领域
prophecy.
预言
And he did not hedge his bet.
他没有闪烁其词
Like Babe Ruth predicting
就像贝比·鲁斯预测
where his next home run would land in the stands,
他的下一个全垒打会落在哪里
Halley stated flatly that the comet would return
哈雷明确地指出这颗彗星
at the end of 1758, from a particular part of the sky,
会在1758年底 出现在天空中的一个特定位置
following a specific path.
遵循一条特定的轨迹
There is hardly a prophecy attempted by the mystics
几乎没有一个由巫师提出的预言
that ever even strives for comparable precision.
能和他的准确性相提并论
That's Halley's Comet.
这就是 哈雷彗星
Out here at the edge of the solar system,
漂浮在太阳系的边缘
it doesn't look like much.
看上去并不大
Just a big hunk of ice and rock in space.
只是太空中一块冰石
That's because beyond the orbit of Neptune,
因为在海王星的轨道以外
nearly five billion kilometers from the Sun,
距离太阳大约50亿公里
comets lead very quiet lives.
彗星过得非常宁静
As it reaches the far end of its orbit,
因为到达了轨道的远端
it'll slow down till the Sun
allows it to go no farther.
它会慢下来 直到太阳将它拉回来
Then it will begin its long fall
back to the inner solar system.
然后它向太阳系的核心坠落
Halley's comet is in free fall around the Sun.
哈雷彗星绕着太阳做自由落体
Everything in our solar system--
the Earth, the Moon,
太阳系中的一切  地球  月亮
the other planets, comets, asteroids,
其他行星  彗星  小行星
all of them are falling around the Sun.
都绕着太阳自由落体
Gravity pulls the planets towards the Sun,
万有引力将它们拉向太阳
but because of their orbital momentum,
但因为它们的轨道动量
they keep moving around the Sun,
never falling into it.
它们保持环绕太阳  而不冲向太阳
Robert Hooke had died years before,
罗伯特·胡克很多年前过世了
having ruined his health
with some bad habits...
一些坏习惯伤害了他的健康
daily doses of wormwood,
opium, mercury.
天天服用苦艾 鸦片 水银
A few months later, Newton was
elected to replace him
几个月后  牛顿取代了他的职位
as president of the Royal Society.
当选皇家学会的会长
It is said that a portrait of Hooke
据说胡克的肖像
once hung on these walls.
曾经挂在这里
Halley lived on to accomplish
many more astonishing feats.
哈雷达成了很多天文学的丰功伟绩
He worked right up to his death at age 85.
他坚持工作到最后一刻 享年85岁
His final act was to call for a glass of wine.
他做的最后一件事是叫了一杯葡萄酒
He downed it with pleasure...
愉快地品下
and breathed his last breath.
呼出最后一口气
Some believe that it was on a night like this
据信在这样的一个夜里
that Isaac Newton finally took his revenge
艾萨克牛顿终于实施了他对
against Robert Hooke.
罗伯特胡克的报复
But Halley's prophecy was not forgotten.
哈雷的预言并未被人遗忘
50 years later,
50年后
as the time of the predicted return approached,
就在预言回归的时间
the world's astronomers vied
全世界的天文学家都希望
to be the first to catch sight of his comet.
第一个观察到 哈雷的彗星
They weren't disappointed.
他们没有失望
It's been welcomed back every 76 years since.
从此以后 每隔76年都有一次观测热潮
When Halley's Comet returns to our skies,
当哈雷彗星回到我们的天空时
sunlight will warm up the ice on its surface,
日光加热它表面的冰
once again setting loose
再一次释放出
the dust and gases trapped within.
内部的灰尘和气体
Halley's Comet most recently visited our neighborhood
哈雷彗星的最近一次回归
back in 1986.
是1986年
And if you're seeing this in 2061,
如果你在2061年看到这个
then you'll know it's back.
你就知道 它回来了
May you feel the wonder of all those
愿你看到眼前的这些
who came before you...
令人惊叹的奇迹时
and none of the fear.
不再害怕
Newton's laws made it possible for Edmond Halley
牛顿定律使爱德蒙哈雷可以预见
to see some 50 years into the future
50年后的未来
and predict the behavior of a single comet.
预测一颗彗星的运动轨迹
Scientists have been using these laws ever since,
科学家们一直使用这些定律
opening the way to the Moon
打开通往月球之路
and even beyond our solar system.
乃至整个太阳系
The baby in the basket is learning to walk...
摇篮中的婴儿开始学习走路了
and to know the cosmos.
开始了解宇宙
Which brings me to one last prophecy.
还有最后一个预言
Using nothing more than Newton's laws of gravitation,
仅仅依靠牛顿的万有引力定律
we astronomers can confidently predict
天文学家可以很确定地预测
that several billion years from now,
几十亿年后
our home galaxy, the Milky Way,
我们的星系  银河系
will merge with our neighboring galaxy Andromeda.
会与我们的邻居 仙女座 交汇
Because the distances between the stars
因为恒星间的距离
are so great compared to their sizes,
相对它们的体积来说 是如此的遥远
few if any stars in either
galaxy will actually collide.
只会有很少数的星星发生碰撞
Any life on the worlds of that far-off future
遥远未来 依然存在的生命
should be safe, but they would
be treated to an amazing,
应该很安全  但是他们可以欣赏到
billion-year-long light show...
持续几十亿年的星光秀
a dance of a half a trillion stars...
几千亿颗星星的群舞
to music first heard on one little world
by a man who had but one true friend.
还有一位伟人与他的挚友共同谱写的精彩乐章
Sync and corrections by n17t01
www.addic7ed.com
中文字幕 @SaltyEggPain